<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title><![CDATA[Tag: hardware | Coconauts]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.github.io/blog/tags/hardware/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
<link href="http://coconauts.github.io/"/>
<updated>2016-03-14T14:53:54+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.github.io/</id>
<author>
<name><![CDATA[Coconauts]]></name>
<email><![CDATA[admin@coconauts.net]]></email>
</author>
<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Honey, I shrunk the Watchduino]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.github.io/blog/2015/10/20/honey-i-shrunk-the-watchduino/"/>
<updated>2015-10-20T22:40:34+01:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.github.io/blog/2015/10/20/honey-i-shrunk-the-watchduino</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend we attended
<a href="http://hackathon.pchintl.com/hackathons/london/2015/10/16/">a hardware hackathon organised by PCH in London</a>.
The theme of the hackathon was &ldquo;Take your prototype to the
next stage in 54 hours&rdquo;, so in our case we brought our
Watchduino prototype and focused on trying to make it closer
to how it would look if it were a commercial product.</p>

<p>The best part is that at the hackathon there was a set of
mentors, people who are experts in different areas of IoT,
which were giving us useful advice about our product
direction, design optimizations or the ins and outs of
manufacturing.</p>

<p>By the end of the hackathon, we had a functional (at least
theorethically) design for Watchduino that looks this
awesome:</p>

<p><img src=https://farm1.staticflickr.com/772/22314247456_e69a4e1275_z_d.jpg' /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The first step to getting a hardware product into manufacturing is integrating all the electronics into a PCB. This not only makes the system easier to put together, it&rsquo;s also smaller, and likely to be more energetically efficient.</p>

<p>So we designed a PCB that would mainly replace the Arduino
Mini, breaking out the pins of the ATMega processor and
leaving space to surface mount the rest of the components.
To completely replace the Arduino board, a 8Mhz crystal
oscillator needs to be added on top of our current
components, as well as breaking out the RX and TX pins for
reprogrammation. It&rsquo;s pretty similar to
<a href="https://bitbucket.org/rephus/watchduino/src/master/docs/how_to_replicate.md">the process we  were following in our first Watchduino</a>.</p>

<p>The board was designed with
<a href="http://fritzing.org">Fritzing</a>,
which we were already
using for our schematic. We were recommended Eagle, which
appears to be the industry standard software, and has
a bigger component library and tons of support online.
But Fritzing is simpler and open source, so it suited
our purposes for the time being. You can find the file
<a href="https://github.com/coconauts/watchduino2/tree/master/schema">on the Github repo</a>.
In the future we would like to try out Eagle though.</p>

<p>By sacrificing the buzzer (which is not really very useful having the vibrator motor) and the USB charching module (to be replaced by a custom connector, as commercial smartwatches usually have) we were able to make our PCB exactly 1 square inch in area. Pretty sweet!</p>

<p><img src='https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5788/21719276463_73d93089ea_o_d.png'/></p>

<p>Being able to mount all the electronics in this small
area mean there&rsquo;s no longer the need to spread them across the strap as they were before. The whole design is
completely compact, and small enough to fit in it&rsquo;s
entirety into a watch head; battery and everything.</p>

<p>In consequence, we redesigned our 3D case into a simpler
shape, looking now very much like a conventional watch!</p>

<p><img src=https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5640/21719246863_26ed9e4423_m_d.jpg' /></p>

<p>We are cheating a little bit, because we are reusing
<a href="https://www.decathlon.co.uk/strap-m-swip-watch-strap-black-id_8243023.html">an existing strap from a Geonaute watch</a>.
These watches are sold at Decathlon stores, and just
happen to have a so handy sliding mechanism for
interchangeable straps.</p>

<p><img src=https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5660/22154594199_2a668aec02_m_d.jpg' /></p>

<p>So we designed our new 3D case
with the same shape, and made it compatible with the
Geonatue straps. Once we figure out how to print with
flexible filament we&rsquo;ll replicate the strap with the
same connector.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s just one thing missing: our sexy new prototype
can&rsquo;t be functional until the PCB is printed (the image
above I&rsquo;m afraid is a dramatization with a screenshot
pasted on it). Printing PCBs can be done manually, but it&rsquo;s handier, better, and often cheaper to just
<a href="http://hackaday.com/2015/09/21/why-are-you-still-making-pcbs/">get a manufacturer to do the job</a>.</p>

<p>When you design a PCB, either with Fritzing, Eagle, or
other software, you can export the result as <em>Gerber files</em>,
which contain all the different layers of your design.
You can provide any PCB manufacturer with this format,
and they&rsquo;ll be able to fabricate a production-quality
version of your board.</p>

<p>So we&rsquo;ve done just that: we ordered a 3-board batch of PCBs to
<a href="https://oshpark.com/">OSH Park</a>, for the outrageous price of just £1 each. We can&rsquo;t wait for them to arrive and see if we can get our first mini production-run of Watchduinos!</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

</feed>