<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title><![CDATA[Tag: template | Coconauts]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/tags/template/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/"/>
<updated>2017-05-01T22:32:42+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/</id>
<author>
<name><![CDATA[Coconauts]]></name>
<email><![CDATA[admin@coconauts.net]]></email>
</author>
<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[RTS game template on Unity3d: StarCraft for mobile]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/01/30/starcraft-mobile-unity3d/"/>
<updated>2016-01-30T20:16:34+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/01/30/starcraft-mobile-unity3d</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have been just <em>playing</em> with Unity3D for a few months, but we have already tried to build something: a new RTS (Real Time Strategy) game for Desktop and Mobile. But we want to make this game abstract and adaptable, so that it works like an engine, which means we could easily change the models, behaviour and statistics from the objects in the scene to make a completely new game, a clone of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Wkrd594k4k">Star Wars Galactic Battlegrounds Clone Campaings</a> maybe ? or maybe completely new strategy game featuring plants vs zombies, pirates vs ninjas, angels vs demons or monkeys vs giraffes.</p>

<p><img src='https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1636/24079670424_3275b9c5f1_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<p>In our case, we&rsquo;ve started by using the 3D models, animations from StarCraft II game
and reverse engineered the behaviour of this game to make our strategy game template.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src='https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1502/24614331371_6e4c44e84e_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<p>Please note that this is just a technical demo and it&rsquo;s not made to replace
StarCraft or make any money with their work in any way, we are just trying to follow their path because we love this game.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="450" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MqGj5grWYG8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>What we have achieved</h2>

<p>This is the list of features we have developed to simulate a basic gameplay from Starcraft.
They together implement the featureset from StarCraft games, but it can be easily applied to fit any other strategy gameplay. Do you want to have 4 different resource types instead of 2 like in SWGB ? just update the Resources class and you&rsquo;re done.</p>

<p><img src='https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1534/24707844895_74afa1c9af_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<ul>
<li>3D models and animations</li>
<li>Background music, sounds and reactions (<em>For Adun!</em>)</li>
<li>Buildings and units training queue</li>
<li>Special building behaviour (like gas extractor or supply depots)</li>
<li>Ground and flying units (Zerg and Terran)</li>
<li>Researches</li>
<li>Resources (Mineral, gas and supplies)</li>
<li>Import maps using image heightmap</li>
<li>Mouse and touch controls</li>
<li>Camera movement and zoom</li>
<li>Completely new simple interface for touch devices</li>
<li>New survival gameplay mode</li>
<li>Basic AI</li>
<li>Minimap</li>
<li>Pathfinding (using free A* pathfinding)</li>
</ul>


<p><img src='https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1452/24681642176_2a5f191b10_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<h2> What is missing</h2>

<p>This are things we haven&rsquo;t build for this prototype but we will probably do in the future.</p>

<ul>
<li>Multiplayer mode</li>
<li>Better AI</li>
<li>Local avoidance</li>
<li>Protoss</li>
<li>More units and buildings (like bunkers)</li>
<li>Wireframe support on OpenGL devices or equivalent</li>
<li>Unit visibility filter</li>
<li>Team coloring</li>
<li>Healing units, shields or Zerg restoration feature.</li>
</ul>


<p>We are planning to release this engine in the future (without the StarCraft assets),
but in the meantime let us know any thoughts in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Add list of featured posts to Octopress]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/09/08/add-featured-posts-to-octopress/"/>
<updated>2015-09-08T19:03:19+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/09/08/add-featured-posts-to-octopress</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago we were requested to add a list of featured posts to an index page in Octopress.
So we did a bit of research about how Octopress + Jekyll + Lyquid template internally works.
And we ended up with a nice solution that you can easily replicate in your own blog.</p>

<p>In this post we will show you how to add your own custom list of featured octopress posts like in <a href="http://coconauts.net#featured-posts">Coconauts</a></p>

<!--more-->


<p>The first thing you need to do is to add a new custom tag to your posts, we will call it <code>featured</code></p>

<h2>```</h2>

<p>layout: post
author: Javier Rengel
published: true</p>

<h2>featured: true</h2>

<p>```</p>

<p>Create a new template file called <code>featured_posts.html</code> inside your <code>source/_includes</code> folder,
with this content:</p>

<p>
```</p>

<div class="row">
   {% assign featured_count = '' %}
   {% for post in site.posts %}
       {% if post.featured and featured_count.size < 3 %}
          {% capture featured_count %}{{ featured_count }}*{% endcapture %}
           <div class="col-sm-4 col-lg-4 column featured-post">
              <a class='post-link' href="{{ root_url }}{{ post.url }}">{{ post.title | titlecase }}</a>
              <p>{{ post.content | strip_html | condense_spaces | truncate:300 }}</p>
           </div>
       {% endif %}
   {% endfor %}
</div>


<p>```
</p>

<p>Then you can list your three most recent featured posts in every page you want just by adding this code to your markdown or HTML file:</p>

<p>
<code>
{% include featured_posts.html %}
</code>
</p>

<p>Just remember to adapt your HTML code and your CSS to your needs (this one is based on <a href="http://getbootstrap.com/">bootstrap</a>).</p>

<h3>Featured posts</h3>

<p><div class="row">
   
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
          
           <div class="col-sm-4 col-lg-4 column">
              <a class='post-link' href="/blog/2016/09/08/smartwatch-prototype-with-esp8266/">Smartwatch Prototype With ESP8266: ESPmartwatch</a>
              <p>It&rsquo;s been a while since we built and deprecated our Watchduino 2 smartwatch built with Arduino and BLE technology. The reason why we stopped developing the prototype was because it was not as optimal as we expected, and the bluetooth communication was unstable in practice; this is probably &hellip;</p>
           </div>
       
   
       
          
           <div class="col-sm-4 col-lg-4 column">
              <a class='post-link' href="/blog/2016/08/01/retrophies/">Retrophies: Achievements System for Emulators</a>
              <p>Play now at retrophies.win! If there’s one thing that has become a de-facto standard in the gaming industry during the last decade this is game achievements, trophies, or whatever you may call them. Not only on console games, but Apple and Android also provide facilities to integrate this features &hellip;</p>
           </div>
       
   
       
          
           <div class="col-sm-4 col-lg-4 column">
              <a class='post-link' href="/blog/2016/06/13/lightning-dodge-o-matic/">Lightning-dodge-O-matic</a>
              <p>If you have played Final Fantasy X, either its original version for PS2 or its remastered version
for PS4 and PSVita, you might remember Thunder Plains and its lightning dodge challenge
to get the Mars sigil. It&rsquo;s quite challenging and it might take a while. I once got it (and I have a PS2 &hellip;</p>
           </div>
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

</feed>