<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title><![CDATA[Tag: watchduino | Coconauts]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/tags/watchduino/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/"/>
<updated>2016-06-29T23:37:04+01:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/</id>
<author>
<name><![CDATA[Coconauts]]></name>
<email><![CDATA[admin@coconauts.net]]></email>
</author>
<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Honey, I shrunk the Watchduino]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/10/20/honey-i-shrunk-the-watchduino/"/>
<updated>2015-10-20T22:40:34+01:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/10/20/honey-i-shrunk-the-watchduino</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend we attended
<a href="http://hackathon.pchintl.com/hackathons/london/2015/10/16/">a hardware hackathon organised by PCH in London</a>.
The theme of the hackathon was &ldquo;Take your prototype to the
next stage in 54 hours&rdquo;, so in our case we brought our
Watchduino prototype and focused on trying to make it closer
to how it would look if it were a commercial product.</p>

<p>The best part is that at the hackathon there was a set of
mentors, people who are experts in different areas of IoT,
which were giving us useful advice about our product
direction, design optimizations or the ins and outs of
manufacturing.</p>

<p>By the end of the hackathon, we had a functional (at least
theorethically) design for Watchduino that looks this
awesome:</p>

<p><img src=https://farm1.staticflickr.com/772/22314247456_e69a4e1275_z_d.jpg' /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The first step to getting a hardware product into manufacturing is integrating all the electronics into a PCB. This not only makes the system easier to put together, it&rsquo;s also smaller, and likely to be more energetically efficient.</p>

<p>So we designed a PCB that would mainly replace the Arduino
Mini, breaking out the pins of the ATMega processor and
leaving space to surface mount the rest of the components.
To completely replace the Arduino board, a 8Mhz crystal
oscillator needs to be added on top of our current
components, as well as breaking out the RX and TX pins for
reprogrammation. It&rsquo;s pretty similar to
<a href="https://bitbucket.org/rephus/watchduino/src/master/docs/how_to_replicate.md">the process we  were following in our first Watchduino</a>.</p>

<p>The board was designed with
<a href="http://fritzing.org">Fritzing</a>,
which we were already
using for our schematic. We were recommended Eagle, which
appears to be the industry standard software, and has
a bigger component library and tons of support online.
But Fritzing is simpler and open source, so it suited
our purposes for the time being. You can find the file
<a href="https://github.com/coconauts/watchduino2/tree/master/schema">on the Github repo</a>.
In the future we would like to try out Eagle though.</p>

<p>By sacrificing the buzzer (which is not really very useful having the vibrator motor) and the USB charching module (to be replaced by a custom connector, as commercial smartwatches usually have) we were able to make our PCB exactly 1 square inch in area. Pretty sweet!</p>

<p><img src='https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5788/21719276463_73d93089ea_o_d.png'/></p>

<p>Being able to mount all the electronics in this small
area mean there&rsquo;s no longer the need to spread them across the strap as they were before. The whole design is
completely compact, and small enough to fit in it&rsquo;s
entirety into a watch head; battery and everything.</p>

<p>In consequence, we redesigned our 3D case into a simpler
shape, looking now very much like a conventional watch!</p>

<p><img src=https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5640/21719246863_26ed9e4423_m_d.jpg' /></p>

<p>We are cheating a little bit, because we are reusing
<a href="https://www.decathlon.co.uk/strap-m-swip-watch-strap-black-id_8243023.html">an existing strap from a Geonaute watch</a>.
These watches are sold at Decathlon stores, and just
happen to have a so handy sliding mechanism for
interchangeable straps.</p>

<p><img src=https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5660/22154594199_2a668aec02_m_d.jpg' /></p>

<p>So we designed our new 3D case
with the same shape, and made it compatible with the
Geonatue straps. Once we figure out how to print with
flexible filament we&rsquo;ll replicate the strap with the
same connector.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s just one thing missing: our sexy new prototype
can&rsquo;t be functional until the PCB is printed (the image
above I&rsquo;m afraid is a dramatization with a screenshot
pasted on it). Printing PCBs can be done manually, but it&rsquo;s handier, better, and often cheaper to just
<a href="http://hackaday.com/2015/09/21/why-are-you-still-making-pcbs/">get a manufacturer to do the job</a>.</p>

<p>When you design a PCB, either with Fritzing, Eagle, or
other software, you can export the result as <em>Gerber files</em>,
which contain all the different layers of your design.
You can provide any PCB manufacturer with this format,
and they&rsquo;ll be able to fabricate a production-quality
version of your board.</p>

<p>So we&rsquo;ve done just that: we ordered a 3-board batch of PCBs to
<a href="https://oshpark.com/">OSH Park</a>, for the outrageous price of just £1 each. We can&rsquo;t wait for them to arrive and see if we can get our first mini production-run of Watchduinos!</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Hackaday price 2015 retrospective]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/10/06/hackaday-price-2015-retrospective/"/>
<updated>2015-10-06T22:40:34+01:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/10/06/hackaday-price-2015-retrospective</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src='https://farm1.staticflickr.com/584/21381222983_a64f947c8d_o_d.png' align='right'/></p>

<p>You may have noticed that the blog has been quite quiet during the last month.
The reason being we were focusing our efforts on doing some epic Watchduino
development, as <a href="https://hackaday.io/project/7244-watchduino2">contestants for the Hackaday Prize 2015</a>.
Sad news in the end though, as we didn&rsquo;t make it to the finals.</p>

<p>But that&rsquo;s ok though. Regardless of the result, this has been a good excercise
for us, and the contest has pushed us to keep working hard on the
<a href="/projects/watchduino2">Watchduino</a> project. That&rsquo;s why we want to
sum up all we have learned and all we have improved on the project during
the course of the contest.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>3D Case</h3>

<p><img class='screenshot' src='https://farm1.staticflickr.com/760/21814249490_2bfe5bf2b9_z_d.jpg'/>
<img class='screenshot' src='https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5717/21815509489_5531e2b080_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<p>One of the things in our TODO list was to build a proper 3D case for our watch,
and thanks to our <a href="https://twitter.com/rephus/status/571811583602647040">3D printer</a> we managed to build a wearable prototype.</p>

<p>We also introduced the Smart Strap design which allows us to keep some of the
electronic components spread along the strap, keeping the watch face smaller.</p>

<p>Our first case design, from a few months ago, was done in <a href="https://www.blender.org/">Blender</a>,
however we&rsquo;ve now switched to <a href="https://tinkercad.com/things/gG641gG1b4c">Tinkercad</a> as it&rsquo;s a great web platform for doing
awesome 3D models really quickly.</p>

<p>We also designed an additional strap prototype using a flexible strap, that we
plan to 3D print soon enough.</p>

<h3>Migration to Cordova</h3>

<p><img class='screenshot' src='https://farm1.staticflickr.com/694/21815557799_9d65cd5172_z_d.jpg'/>
<img class='screenshot' src='https://farm1.staticflickr.com/668/21814312750_9f80cebaa1_b_d.jpg'/></p>

<p>A few weeks before we joined the contest, we started migrating the existing
Android companion app, written natively, to the Cordova framework.</p>

<p>The reason for this is because Cordova seems a better platform for us, based
on HTML5 + JS, and multiplatform. It&rsquo;s easier and faster to develop with,
the codebase is smaller, and in general we are quite happy with it!</p>

<p>We finally migrated all the code with a better design by the end of August,
and we even introduced new functionality.</p>

<h3>Showcase videos</h3>

<p>We made two videos to showcase the capabilities of the watch.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="500" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/n-ubg1R2e-A" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>




<iframe width="100%" height="500" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LVE85OxWGzs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h3>Open source code and documentation</h3>

<p>One of the requirements of the project was to release our code and build our
documentation so everyone can create a new Watchduino from scratch.</p>

<p>This has been in our roadmap for ages, so it was a good excuse to clean up
the code a bit an make it public.</p>

<p>Feel free to <a href="https://github.com/coconauts/watchduino2">clone our project</a>, and to make pull request to improve our own.</p>

<p>Be warned though: the codebase is still under heavy development, so things
might change drastically from one day to the next!</p>

<h3>Next steps</h3>

<p>The community also helped us to improve our watch architecture and we are keen on
trying different approaches so Watchduino can be even better than it&rsquo;s now.</p>

<p>One of the main objectives is to improve the Bluetooth connectivity and
the power consumption. Another one is to make an app creation framework that is
lean and easy to use.</p>

<p>Stay tuned for more updates, are we are definitely not done with our
Watchduino development!</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[WatchDuino 2 is semifinalist on the 2015 Hackaday Prize]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/08/24/watchduino-2-is-semifinalist-on-the-2015-hackaday-prize/"/>
<updated>2015-08-24T20:18:35+01:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/08/24/watchduino-2-is-semifinalist-on-the-2015-hackaday-prize</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/hackaday_semifinal.png" /></p>

<p>We are really excited to announce that <a href="https://www.coconauts.net/projects/watchduino2/">WatchDuino 2</a> has passed to
<a href="http://hackaday.com/2015/08/24/100-semifinalists-for-the-2015-hackaday-prize/">the semi-finals of the 2015 edition of the Hackaday Prize</a>!
It was selected amongst the best 100 of a total of more than 900 projects.
To see this kind of recognition out of a community that we admire is
absolutely thrilling, thank you so much =)</p>

<p>This means that now we will have to give our best we want to be good enough
to be in the finals. Many other excellent projects are competing!</p>

<p>Keep an eye on the <a href="https://hackaday.io/project/7244-watchduino2">project page on Hackaday</a>,
as it is likely to be holding exciting updates and advancements during the
following month. And give us your skulls and likes if you have an account! =)</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Watchduino 2 first prototype]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/02/26/watchduino2-first-prototype/"/>
<updated>2015-02-26T20:42:14+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/02/26/watchduino2-first-prototype</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Five weeks have passed since I built the first wearable prototype of Watchduino 2,
and I would like to share with you my impressions, its current features and its possible improvements.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/watchduino2-prototype/all-3.jpg" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Software</h2>

<p>The software is running in an Arduino Mini Pro v2 3.3v 8Mhz and spans across 1588 lines of code, 17 files and 9 different classes.</p>

<p>This code takes 28.212 bytes of the ATMega328&rsquo;s ROM and everything uses 1200 bytes of RAM when running.</p>

<p>Apart from that, there is an Android app for comunication which provides cool features like a a Twitter client for our smartwatch.</p>

<h2>Hardware</h2>

<p>We need to talk about new hardware for Watchduino 2,
as it is very different from its <a href="http://www.coconauts.net/projects/watchduino/">first version</a>
which makes this new version smaller, prettier and more useful.</p>

<ul>
<li>Arduino mini pro 2 8Mhz 3.3v</li>
<li>LIPO battery 240mah</li>
<li>0.96" I2C 128X64 OLED (Various colors)</li>
<li>3 x 6 x 4.3mm Push Button 2 Pin</li>
<li>0.06A Micro Vibrator Motor</li>
<li>Micro USB LIPO charger</li>
<li>Bluetooth 3.0 module HC-06</li>
</ul>


<p>We have built 2 (and a half) prototypes following the same specification.</p>

<h2>Features</h2>

<p>Thanks to this new hardware, we managed to add new features to this new version.
Most of them were mentioned in the <a href="http://www.coconauts.net/blog/2014/11/22/watchduino-2-dot-0-roadmap/">Watchduino roadmap post</a>,
but you can have another look here:</p>

<h3>Companion app (Android)</h3>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/watchduino2-prototype/manager.png" class="screenshot" /></p>

<p>This is a big one, thanks to the bluetooth module we are able to send and receive messages from and to Android
in realtime. This is a list of the features already available.</p>

<ul>
<li>Time sync: Set up the time sending a short message from the phone with the current timestamp, bye bye RTC.</li>
<li>Weather information: Use weather APIs in the phone to get weather information (temperature, sky, humidity, etc)</li>
<li>Twitter client: Read your twitter timeline from your watch (Awesome!!)</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/watchduino2-prototype/twitter.jpg" class="screenshot" /></p>

<ul>
<li>Notifications: Get notifications on your watch (emails, twits, whatsapp&hellip;)
using the recent NotificationListener feature in Android.</li>
<li>Debug: Great for debugging, send any message from the watch to your phone.</li>
<li>Battery: Send battery messages from the watch to the phone to watch how the battery decreases with time</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/watchduino2-prototype/battery.png" class="screenshot" /></p>

<p>But honestly, you can build whatever feature you want using your phone and a few APIs.
Facebook client maybe ? Automatic whatsapp responses ?</p>

<p>Actually, we are working in the following features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Bus notifications (see how long does your bus take to arrive, using the Transport For London APIs)</li>
<li>Settings: Managed from the android app, and stored in the phone.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Screens</h3>

<p>New screens, new resolution (128x64) and new style, with dynamic in-screen information for the buttons.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/watchduino2-prototype/watch.jpg" class="screenshot"/></p>

<p>Screen navigation is easier now with this simple menu.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/watchduino2-prototype/menu.jpg" class="screenshot" /></p>

<h3>Notifications</h3>

<p>A vibrator and a tiny buzzer will alert you when a notification arrives.</p>

<p>Also, the buzzer can play short melodies for alarms and whatnot.</p>

<h3>Battery life</h3>

<p>Using a tiny 240mah battery and without any kind of energy optimization (on-screen, bluetooth always on)
a single charge last around 10 hours.</p>

<p>Also, you can always look at your remaining battery in the top bar of the screen (like in phones).</p>

<p>The charging time is less than 20 minutes.</p>

<p>The problem here is the bluetooth module (HC-06), I was able to reduce its consumption to 4mA in sleep mode,
but even so, the device would last up to 40 hours, which is not enough.
No more optimisations can be performed from our side,
so at this point I think the only option would be to try with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetooth_low_energy">Bluetooth BLE</a>.</p>

<h2>Possible improvements</h2>

<p>It works cool so far, but it can be improved a lot (there are still a few bugs).
However that may require some time and maybe a new prototype.
In short term, this are the things we are going to focus in the next weeks.</p>

<ul>
<li>Better case (3D printed?).</li>
<li>Fix missing characters from Watchduino to Android.</li>
<li>New charging system.</li>
<li>Improve Battery life with Bluetooth BLE.</li>
<li>Save settings in Android.</li>
<li>Bring back the alarm / countdown features from Watchduino v1.</li>
<li>Memory ROM and RAM can be optimized.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Watchduino 2.0 roadmap]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2014/11/22/watchduino-2-dot-0-roadmap/"/>
<updated>2014-11-22T19:52:37+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2014/11/22/watchduino-2-dot-0-roadmap</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/watchduino-roadmap/components.jpeg" /></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s been some time since we gave you some updates about Watchduino,
but we haven&rsquo;t forgotten about the project. In fact, we can&rsquo;t stop
planning what will be the next exciting feature that we want to try to
develop. For this reason, we&rsquo;ve put together a roadmap of the set of
features we want the next version of Watchduino to include:</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Watchduino 2.0 roadmap:</p>

<ul>
<li>Bluetooth communication between Watchduino and Android phones

<ul>
<li>Android phone refers all notifications to Watchduino</li>
<li>Watchduino to show notifications</li>
<li>Dismiss notifications from Watchduino, they will be dismissed from phone as well</li>
<li>Ping utility to check connection</li>
<li>Time sync from phone</li>
<li>Once Bluetooth is working, more exciting features will come!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Vibration

<ul>
<li>Vibrate with notifications and alarms</li>
<li>Can be disabled through options</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Better screen

<ul>
<li>Choose a better screen with more resolution. And perhaps even colors?</li>
<li>Current candidates:</li>
<li>0.9'&lsquo; 128x64 B&amp;W OLED display</li>
<li>1.8'&lsquo; 128x160 color TFT display</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Better speaker</li>
<li>Better design

<ul>
<li>Integrated PCB (more compact design)</li>
<li>3D printed case?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Programming framework improvements</li>
</ul>


<p>In essence, we would like to make Watchduino as useful as other commercial
smartwatches. We have in fact already started to work on some of this. For instance&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/watchduino-roadmap/notifications-bluetooth.jpeg" /></p>

<p>We are already able to refer Android notifications to Watchduino via Bluetooth.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/watchduino-roadmap/bluetooth.jpeg" /></p>

<p>We have a prototype management Android app to aid with testing and setting up the
Bluetooth connection.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/watchduino-roadmap/screens.jpg" /></p>

<p>An we&rsquo;ve also started tinkering with new screen models.</p>

<p>To make all of this possible, we first invested some effort in doing a huge memory
optimization to the code, that gives us a lot more room for programming customizations.</p>

<p>We are also planning to do a little bit of research in the following areas,
though some of these may turn out to be unachievable for Watchduino&rsquo;s requirements:</p>

<ul>
<li>Wireless charging

<ul>
<li>Watchduino to integrate a wireless charging receiver module, instead of USB port</li>
<li>This opens the door to having a water proof case</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Memory extension

<ul>
<li>Integrate a 23K256 SRAM module</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Voice control</li>
<li>Touchscreen</li>
</ul>


<p>So keep an eye on the blog, as we will be posting advancements and interesting results
as we go through the development of the features. Each step will bring us closer to
the ultimate hacker smartwatch!</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

</feed>