<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: General | Coconauts]]></title>
  <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/categories/general/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://coconauts.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-05-16T08:04:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://coconauts.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Coconauts]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[admin@coconauts.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coconauts 2016 Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/12/30/coconauts-2016-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-30T21:11:39+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/12/30/coconauts-2016-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another year went by, and this is the third that we find ourselves writing
a retrospective in the blog, not bad eh?
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z04M6NhkIKk">2016 hasn&rsquo;t been too cheerful</a>
(at least not for fans of the many stars that have left us this year,
or for people with progressive political views in general).</p>

<p>When it comes to Coconauts however it didn&rsquo;t go too bad:</p>

<ul>
<li>Perhaps the biggest highlight of the year is the
<a href="http://retrophies.win/">Retrophies project</a>. Featured in
<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12205560">HackerNews</a> and
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/emulation/comments/4voi81/retrophies_achievements_system_for_emulators/">Reddit</a>.
We started it as an experiment that turned out to be successful,
and we are still expanding it (for instance, the latest addition was a
<a href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/12/29/how-improve-nintendo/">multiplayer mario game using websockets</a>).</li>
<li>We&rsquo;ve been experimenting with the ESP8266 chip, as a more versatile,
powerful and cheaper alternative to Arduino, and we started
<a href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/09/08/smartwatch-prototype-with-esp8266/http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/09/08/smartwatch-prototype-with-esp8266/">migrating Watchduino to the ESP8266</a>.</li>
<li>A small hack that also turned out to be a hit is the
<a href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/06/13/lightning-dodge-o-matic/">Lightning-dodge-O-matic</a>,
featured on <a href="http://hackaday.com/2016/06/22/cheating-at-video-games-arduino-edition/http://hackaday.com/2016/06/22/cheating-at-video-games-arduino-edition/">Hackaday</a>!</li>
<li>We published our <a href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/02/04/coconauts-ci-nodejs/">custom mini-CI system</a></li>
<li>We started the year working on a <a href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/01/30/starcraft-mobile-unity3d/http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/01/30/starcraft-mobile-unity3d/">mobile version of Starcraft</a> (which we shortly after stopped working on, but there&rsquo;s still a demo video).</li>
</ul>


<p>Our plans of focusing on game making haven&rsquo;t materialized as much as we would have liked.
We&rsquo;ve also continued blogging very little during the year; although, there is one
aspect where we have delivered: more frequent status updates about ongoing projects. Thanks to this,
we&rsquo;ve shown you some prototyes and smaller projects through the year despite not
having any big reveals.</p>

<p>So what are our best whishes for 2017? Pretty much the same as the year before:</p>

<ul>
<li>More games</li>
<li>More open source</li>
<li>More frequent blogging</li>
<li>More awesome</li>
</ul>


<p>See you in 2017, have a good one! =)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Pi Day!]]></title>
    <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/03/14/happy-pi-day/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-14T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/03/14/happy-pi-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you know what day is today? It&rsquo;s 3.14, and because it matches the
decimals in the most beloved irrational number ever, it&rsquo;s been called an
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pi_Day">official celebration of number Pi</a>.</p>

<p>Actually last year it was a most special instance, as it was 3.14.15; an
event that won&rsquo;t occur again for another 100 years! To celebrate, and to
give some use to our newly bought 3D printer, we printed some <a href="http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:28882">Pi-shaped
cookie-cutters we found off Thingiverse</a>,
and baked some delicious Pi&hellip; cookies.</p>

<p><img src="https://thingiverse-production-new.s3.amazonaws.com/renders/42/94/15/17/a7/IMG_20150312_223708_preview_featured.jpg" /></p>

<p>This year still feels special, as it is 3.14.16, the decimals of <em>rounded</em> Pi.
If you wanna celebrate, and have a 3D printer yourself, have a look at
<a href="http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:28882">this neat collection</a> they&rsquo;ve put
together, and print yourself something awesome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coconauts 2015 Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/01/01/year-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-01T14:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/01/01/year-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Year 2015 has come to an end, and as it turns out we do have
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-balancing_two-wheeled_board">hoverboards</a>,
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vZRFcGrrsyc">holograms/augmented reality</a>,
yet for some reason hip-kids insist in dressing as lumberjacks rather than
in futuristic clothing.</p>

<p>It feels just like yesterday when we were writing
<a href="https://coconauts.net/blog/2014/12/31/coconauts-2014-retrospective/">our retrospective post</a>
last year. Time does fly! So how did we fare this year in comparison?</p>

<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li>The <a href="https://coconauts.net/projects/watchduino2/">second version of Watchduino</a>
was an absolute smash. We managed to get a functional prototype with
Bluetooth connectivity, plus a phone companion app. It&rsquo;s starting to
look something like a real smartwatch, and it was awarded
<a href="https://coconauts.net/blog/2015/08/24/watchduino-2-is-semifinalist-on-the-2015-hackaday-prize/">semifinalist in the Hackaday Prize</a>.</li>
<li>Our second big release of the year, even if it was a bit last minute,
was the long promised open sourcing of
<a href="https://coconauts.net/blog/2015/12/31/gramola-release/">Gramola</a>,
a web-based music player.</li>
<li>Smaller projects, but let&rsquo;s not forget about:
<a href="https://coconauts.net/blog/2015/10/13/notification-listener-android-cordova/">a notification listener plugin for Cordova</a>,
<a href="https://coconauts.net/blog/2015/04/22/simple-automatic-watering-system-arduino/">an Arduino automated watering system</a>,
our <a href="https://coconauts.net/blog/2015/07/31/404-games/">404-games</a>.</li>
<li>Seems like we still aren&rsquo;t blogging as much as we should, as we have some
extra small projects that we didn&rsquo;t tell you about in the blog:
<a href="https://github.com/coconauts/image-to-json">an image-to-json</a> converter,
<a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam/rate/43682">a generative game</a> made for the
<a href="http://www.procjam.com/">PROCJAM</a> game jam, and
<a href="https://github.com/coconauts/find-open">a webapp to find open restaurants near you</a>.</li>
<li>We didn&rsquo;t blog as much as we would have liked, but even so we brought
you a bunch of tutorials about
<a href="https://coconauts.net/blog/tags/arduino/">Arduino</a>,
<a href="https://coconauts.net/blog/tags/unity3d/">Unity3D</a>, or
<a href="https://coconauts.net/blog/tags/chiptune/">chiptune music</a>, among others.</li>
</ul>


<p>The year certainly felt as packed as the year before, so we definitely
want to keep the momentum going for 2016. Here&rsquo;s our immediate plans for
the year to come:</p>

<ul>
<li>We didn&rsquo;t do as much gamedev as we would have liked during 2015, so we
would like to finish a Unity3D game during the next year. Specially now that
<a href="http://blogs.unity3d.com/es/2015/08/26/unity-comes-to-linux-experimental-build-now-available/">Unity3D is available for Linux</a>,
there&rsquo;s no better time!</li>
<li>Once again, we want to aim to do more and better posting. 2015 saw
regular blog updates until october, but for this year we want to do
even better.</li>
<li>To help fatten our blog and Github account, we want to commit to talk
about our projects even while in an early stage. Instead of doing the
development of a game or project in the dark until it is polished enough to
show (as done with <a href="https://coconauts.net/projects/timebomb2/">Exploding Bunnies</a>
or <a href="https://coconauts.net/projects/gramola/">Gramola</a>)
we want to to show prototypes and betas as early as we
have them, and keep our development more open
(as we have done with <a href="https://coconauts.net/projects/watchduino2/">Watchduino2</a>).</li>
<li>Speaking of Watchduino2, we plan to continue it&rsquo;s development due to
popular demand, albeit perhaps at a slower pace than we did during 2015.</li>
</ul>


<p>Wishing a happy and exciting 2016 for all our followers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coconauts 2014 Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2014/12/31/coconauts-2014-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-31T17:24:14+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2014/12/31/coconauts-2014-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every time there&rsquo;s a change of year we can&rsquo;t help taking a look back to
account for everything that is different from the same point one year ago.
For Coconauts 2014 has been a really exciting year, and we wanted to have a
record of our achievements during the same, so when we take a look back again
at the end of 2015 we have something to compare against.</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>We <a href="http://www.coconauts.net/blog/2014/04/30/watchduino-awarded-first-price-at-biicontest-2014/">won the Biicode 2014 competition with Watchduino</a>.
We are also <a href="http://www.coconauts.net/blog/2014/11/22/watchduino-2-dot-0-roadmap/">working on an improved version</a>,
so we&rsquo;ll have some more work for next year.</li>
<li>We <a href="http://www.coconauts.net/blog/2014/05/10/coconauts-is-powered-by-octopress/">migrated our blog from Wordpress to Octopress</a>,
and we started blogging regularly on it.</li>
<li>We <a href="http://www.coconauts.net/blog/2014/09/15/super-time-bomb-is-out/">released Super Time Bomb</a>,
our second LibGDX game for Android. We also did a couple of seasonal updates for it.</li>
<li>You may have missed it, because we didn&rsquo;t blog about it, but we released a
<a href="http://www.coconauts.net/projects/game-manager/">Web Game Manager</a> desktop app
(written in node.js).</li>
<li>We opened a <a href="https://github.com/coconauts">Github account</a>, where we will
place all new pieces of public code from now on.</li>
<li>Minor projects we&rsquo;ve shown you include a <a href="http://www.coconauts.net/blog/2014/08/02/web-screensaver/">Chromium based screensaver</a>,
<a href="http://www.coconauts.net/blog/2014/09/03/send-readings-from-arduino-to-raspberry-via-radio/">wireless radio Arduino sensors</a>,
and a <a href="http://www.coconauts.net/blog/2014/08/14/meteorological-station-with-rasbperry-pi-phase-1/">meteorological station powered by a Raspberry Pi</a>.</li>
<li>Internally, we have a much better organization and logistics. We started
using <a href="http://trello.com">Trello</a> for task management, and <a href="http://www.coconauts.net/blog/2014/09/09/background-tasks-in-jenkins-ipchange/">Jenkins and Ansible for
automated operations</a>.</li>
<li>We&rsquo;ve also started a bunch of new projects, but they are still on a very early
stage, so we haven&rsquo;t shown anything about them yet. Hopefully some of them
will grow to a point where they can be published during the next year.</li>
</ul>


<p>So we are quite happy to see the big leaps taken during the year. We expect 2015
to be at least just as exciting, if not even more! We are in fact going as far
as to state a series of commitments:</p>

<ul>
<li>To finally open source Gramola (we&rsquo;ve actually rewritten it from scratch
during the year!).</li>
<li>To have a working Watchduino 2.0 prototype.</li>
<li>To release at least another game or app.</li>
<li>To blog more and better than we&rsquo;ve done this year.</li>
</ul>


<p>And on top of all this, we the Coconauts wish all our readers and followers
a happy and prosperous year 2015. We are really excited about it because&hellip;
it&rsquo;s finally the &ldquo;future&rdquo; according to the Back to the Future movies!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coconauts Now Is Powered by Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2014/05/10/coconauts-is-powered-by-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-10T10:44:38+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2014/05/10/coconauts-is-powered-by-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may have noticed that the design of our website has changed slightly recently. This is because we have migrated the software that powers it, from Wordpress to Octopress.</p>

<p>Wordpress is a very stable and easy to use blogging framework, written in PHP, and backed by a MySQL database. It&rsquo;s so easy to use in fact that is not uncommon to see it being used to power not only blogs,
but also simple websites that don require a lot of application logic. It&rsquo;s got a very friendly administration interface, so that once it&rsquo;s been set up it&rsquo;s very easy to use by
redactors without any tech knowledge.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Wordpress has several problems though. First, all of your content must be held in a database, so it is cumbersome to extract it out of the blog, if you ever wanted to.
Dynamic websites are also less safe than static ones, and require more processing power to serve them. And if you ever tried migrating a Wordpress site, well, is definitely doable,
but not as simple as just copying and pasting your files and database from one server to another.</p>

<p>So recently, there&rsquo;s been a trend of going back to static websites when you don&rsquo;t need dynamic capabilities. But instead of writing the HTML pages directly, the new cool is using
a website generator: so you can write your context in a friendly markup language (like Markdown, or RestructuredText), and then call the software to generate the HTML website.
Such website is static, and can be hosted practically anywhere, even in Github Pages or Dropbox!</p>

<p>Writing your content in a markup language has several advantages over using a WYSIWYG editor in a webapp, and keeping the content in a database. To begin with, you don&rsquo;t need a database!
One thing less to worry about. Your blog content is perfectly accessible and readable in raw text files, without needing to go and query it out a database. Also, you can keep all
of your site&rsquo;s content under version control. How cool is that?</p>

<p>So for Coconauts we are now using Octopress, as we think is the more simple and convenient static website generator around. You write your content in Markdown (our favorite markup
language), use a command to generate your static site, and then your'r off to deploy it. In our case, we have a Jenkings polling our version control repo, so it auto-deploys it every
time we make a <code>git push</code>. Octopress also comes It comes with a lot of features built in, like Twitter buttons, or Google Analytics, and you can add more plugins or tweak all pages you want directly.</p>

<p>As they say, it&rsquo;s &ldquo;A blogging framework for hackers&rdquo; so if you feel brave enough <a href="http://octopress.org/">give it a try</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
