<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title><![CDATA[Tag: game | Coconauts]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/tags/game/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/"/>
<updated>2017-02-21T21:00:06+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/</id>
<author>
<name><![CDATA[Coconauts]]></name>
<email><![CDATA[admin@coconauts.net]]></email>
</author>
<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[We built our house with Unity3D and Blender]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/05/19/build-house-in-3d-with-blender-unity3d/"/>
<updated>2016-05-19T22:51:00+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/05/19/build-house-in-3d-with-blender-unity3d</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We moved home a few months ago to a beautiful house in the country side in UK,
outside the expensive area of London, but close enough to commute daily.</p>

<p>As soon as we moved in, we built a simple version of our home in 3D on Blender
 to help us decorate. And then we integrated the 3D model into Unity3D and build
a game on top of it, on this case, a FPS or more like a FPW: First Person Walker,
a FPS without shooting, not as fun as it sounds.</p>

<p>We posted an image on Twitter a few months ago about our first prototype:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I finally created a First person game of my new home with <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/unity3D?src=hash">#unity3D</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/blender?src=hash">#blender</a> . Looks better than real life! <a href="https://t.co/JjSPPP1835">pic.twitter.com/JjSPPP1835</a></p>&mdash; Javi Rengel (@rephus) <a href="https://twitter.com/rephus/status/698998470280089600">February 14, 2016</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>




<!-- more -->


<p>And this is how our place looks after we bought all the furniture.</p>

<p><img src='https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7236/26513350403_4ac3cc142c_z_d.jpg'/>
<img src='https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7714/27083818276_36950ff772_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<p><img src='https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7715/27083819056_acb9ae8fa5_z_d.jpg'/>
<img src='https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7348/27083818686_12b5f68383_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<p><img src='https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7211/27083819206_727a82707c_z_d.jpg'/>
<img src='https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7434/26513349443_4d9df59b0d_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<p><img src='https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7750/27083819266_15ca7674e5_z_d.jpg'/>
<img src='https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7054/27083818506_f84f07ba12_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<p>The game is also a good chance to try out VR, perfect to use with Google VR to feel
like you are at home.</p>

<p><img src='https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7554/27083819136_dd3a9a50d3_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<p>If you are interested, you can play on our 3D model we made, please feel at home.</p>

<p><a href="http://unity3d.coconauts.net/welwyn">Play it here!</a></p>
]]></content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Building 3D virtual reality games with Unity3D]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/06/20/3d-virtual-reality-demo-with-unity/"/>
<updated>2015-06-20T15:53:19+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/06/20/3d-virtual-reality-demo-with-unity</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>All the big companies like Samsung, Sony and even Facebook are doing their best to build the
ultimate Virtual Reality headset and make it standard.</p>

<p>Once they are in the market, we (indie game developers) need to be ready to build VR games
so everyone can enjoy their fancy expensive devices.</p>

<p>So, in order to start playing with them, you could either pay 350$ dollars for a <a href="https://www.oculus.com/order/">Oculus Rift developing kit</a>,
or you could get one of those cheap kits from <a href="http://www.aliexpress.com/item/High-quality-DIY-Google-Cardboard-Virtual-Reality-VR-Mobile-Phone-3D-Glasses-for-5-0-Screen/32301733749.html?s=p">Google</a>
or even <a href="https://twitter.com/rephus/status/587297530045714432">build your own</a>, and start building games in Unity3D.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/3d-island-demo/img1.png" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>We recently built a VR technical demo in Unity and it&rsquo;s available on <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.coconauts.island3d">Play store</a>.
The purpose of this demo was built to test the performance of a Virtual Reality environment in Unity3D.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/3d-island-demo/img2.png" /></p>

<p>It uses the scene and models from the <a href="http://unity3d.com/showcase/live-demos#tropical-paradise">Tropical Paradise Unity demo</a>,</p>

<p>But because this demo was built for Unity v3 and we use 4.6 we had to fix some parts of the code to make it compatible,
also we replaced the water effect completely with a new one for the free version.</p>

<p>Also, it&rsquo;s optimized for mobile platforms and we included some simple features to make it VR ready.</p>

<p>We noticed that the game runs great in PC, and OK (~30FPS) in a modern phone even with high resolution and good quality.
The bottleneck is the number of details and shadows in the scene, or drawCalls in unity.</p>

<p>But you can try by your own by <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.coconauts.island3d">downloading</a> the game into your phone.</p>

<p>If you have a question or want more details about our demo, please let us know in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploding Bunnies]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/03/21/exploding-bunnies/"/>
<updated>2015-03-21T15:53:19+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/03/21/exploding-bunnies</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been half a year since
<a href="http://www.coconauts.net/projects/timebomb2/">Super Time Bomb</a>
was released. During this
time, we&rsquo;ve been closely following it&rsquo;s reception, and gathering user
feedback. Today we released an update with major gameplay changes,
including a name change!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>New name</h2>

<p>The game is now named <em>Exploding Bunnies</em>, in the hope that this is
a more unique name, making it easier to search on the Play Store.
Before it was appearing over the 10th position in the search result,
whereas now it&rsquo;s showing up the forth, you don&rsquo;t even need to scroll
to see it.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/exploding-bunnies/store.png" /></p>

<h2>More fun difficulty curve</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ve made the difficulty curve more stable. Previously, the difficulty
in both game modes was set to be strictly incremental: it started
really slow and easy, and difficult went up at a constant rate. But
after a few minutes it turned out to be humanely impossible to survive.
This made for a frustrating experience, with short gameplays, boring time
after every restart, and no incentive for players to try to last longer
and longer, since it was physically impossible.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve heavily tuned the difficulty curve so that now starts out a little
bit more upbeat, so you won&rsquo;t be bored with every game restart. Then it
goes up  until it reaches a limit at 5 minutes of gameplay, after which
point it will stabilize. This allows for in theory infinite gameplays,
giving the players an incentive to keep trying to beat their high scores.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/exploding-bunnies/difficulty.png" /></p>

<h2>One game mode to rule them all</h2>

<p>The original Super Time Bomb included two game modes: wave and continous.
For this revision, however, we&rsquo;ve decided to say goodbyde to the wave mode
and keep the continous one. The wave mode wasn&rsquo;t that different from the
continous one, so it was a bit redundant to begin with. The difficulty
curve problem mentioned earlier was also more accused in the wave mode
than in the continous one. It also confused new users trying out the game
to have to pick between two game modes.</p>

<p>So now we have one big &ldquo;PLAY&rdquo; button instead, which will take you to
the formerly continous mode gameplay. Unite and conquer!</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/exploding-bunnies/mainmenu.png" /></p>

<h2>Death from above</h2>

<p>Since we&rsquo;ve limited the difficulty in terms of quantity of bombs in the
screen, we&rsquo;ve decided to add a new type of bomb to increase the complexity
a little bit. Now, aside from the regular bombs, mines, and wall lasers,
we have a new dropping bomb that falls from the sky. The difference is that
for this type of bomb there is no counter! You&rsquo;ll just see a warning and
a shadow where the bomb will fall.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/exploding-bunnies/airbomb.png" /></p>

<h2>Go play it!</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s difficult to make a star game in your first shot. Usually most
great games come from successive iterations over the same idea (just
have a look at the metal gear games for instance!).</p>

<p>So go and give a try to the new
<a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.coconauts.timebomb2">Exploding Bunnies</a>
and see how you like it! Please give us feedback: we welcome every
comment, and we&rsquo;ll try to make the next iteration even better.</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

</feed>