<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title><![CDATA[Tag: pi | Coconauts]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/tags/pi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/"/>
<updated>2017-02-07T22:18:29+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/</id>
<author>
<name><![CDATA[Coconauts]]></name>
<email><![CDATA[admin@coconauts.net]]></email>
</author>
<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Build a smart home using Raspberry Pi and Energenie]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/04/15/energinie-and-raspberry-pi-setup/"/>
<updated>2016-04-15T22:51:00+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/04/15/energinie-and-raspberry-pi-setup</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We recently discovered <a href="https://energenie4u.co.uk/">Energenie</a> (thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/Man0jN">Manoj</a>) a nice and cheap remote controlled socket
which also provides a custom shield for Raspberry Pi, you can use it to
programatically control those sockets. This allows endless possibilities:
from temporized sockets, to a socket that automatically turns on when
detects presence using a PIR sensor, or triggered by a website or a phone app.</p>

<p><img src='https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1545/25845471424_d600499717_d.jpg'/></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>You can buy 2 different types of Energenie, some <a href="https://energenie4u.co.uk/catalogue/product/ENER002-4">individual sockets</a>
or an <a href="https://energenie4u.co.uk/catalogue/product/ENER010">extension lead socket with 4 individually controlled</a>.
You can also find them cheaper on Amazon or <a href="http://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/161972721449?_trksid=p2060353.m2749.l2649&amp;ssPageName=STRK%3AMEBIDX%3AIT">Ebay</a>.</p>

<p>Every Energenie comes with a remote that you can use to power on or off those sockets using radio
(no need to point with the controller to the socket like an infrared remote).
You can use them just like this, but of course the really fun part is to be able
to program them with your Raspberry Pi. For this, you&rsquo;ll need the
<a href="https://energenie4u.co.uk/catalogue/product/ENER314">control board shield</a>
as well.</p>

<p>You can download a library for Python to use with Raspberry Pi from <a href="http://pythonhosted.org/energenie/">their website</a>, and check some examples of basic usage.</p>

<p>In our case, as our first project, we built a website so you can control all
sockets in the extension lead from your
computer. In one of them we added some Cinema style lights under our sofa using a
LED strip connected to a 12V supplier on the socket.</p>

<p><img src='https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1704/26449115715_b672c53b20_z_d.jpg'/>
<img src='https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1652/26449115515_60a9fd10a7_z_d.jpg'/></p>

<p>The interface looks like this:</p>

<p><img src='https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1630/26423191956_b64967a883_o_d.png'/></p>

<p>You can check the source code in our <a href="https://github.com/rephus/energenie-manager">Github</a>.</p>

<h3>Warnings and limitations</h3>

<p>Each Raspberry PI board or remote allows you to use 4 different sockets
(or 1 extension lead)  maximum. Which means you can&rsquo;t have for example 5 sockets
controlled with a single Raspberry Pi.</p>

<p>Each socket can only be paired with 2 controllers maximum, which means you can&rsquo;t control a socket with a remote and 2 Raspberry Pis. Every time you pair a new socket, the oldest one will get unpaired. Also, remember to pair every device before using it or it won&rsquo;t work.</p>

<p>Do you have more ideas to implement with Energenie? we&rsquo;d like to hear about them in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Pi Day!]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/03/14/happy-pi-day/"/>
<updated>2016-03-14T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/03/14/happy-pi-day</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you know what day is today? It&rsquo;s 3.14, and because it matches the
decimals in the most beloved irrational number ever, it&rsquo;s been called an
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pi_Day">official celebration of number Pi</a>.</p>

<p>Actually last year it was a most special instance, as it was 3.14.15; an
event that won&rsquo;t occur again for another 100 years! To celebrate, and to
give some use to our newly bought 3D printer, we printed some <a href="http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:28882">Pi-shaped
cookie-cutters we found off Thingiverse</a>,
and baked some delicious Pi&hellip; cookies.</p>

<p><img src="https://thingiverse-production-new.s3.amazonaws.com/renders/42/94/15/17/a7/IMG_20150312_223708_preview_featured.jpg" /></p>

<p>This year still feels special, as it is 3.14.16, the decimals of <em>rounded</em> Pi.
If you wanna celebrate, and have a 3D printer yourself, have a look at
<a href="http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:28882">this neat collection</a> they&rsquo;ve put
together, and print yourself something awesome.</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

</feed>