<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Games | Coconauts]]></title>
  <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/categories/games/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://coconauts.net/"/>
  <updated>2017-05-30T12:43:01+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://coconauts.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Coconauts]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[admin@coconauts.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bank Holiday Hackday: Escape Room on Unity3D]]></title>
    <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2017/05/29/bank-holiday-hackday-escape-room-on-unity3d/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-29T20:00:14+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2017/05/29/bank-holiday-hackday-escape-room-on-unity3d</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s another bank holiday in England, and in Coconauts this means: hackday!</p>

<p>Last time we did an <a href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2017/05/01/infinify-an-infinite-discovery-mode-for-spotify/">infinite recommender for Spotify</a>,
and this time  we wanted to get started with a game concept that has been in our heads for a while: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Escape_room">a escape room</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2017-05-29-escape-room/room.png" alt="Room" /></p>

<p>Our idea came after playing the <a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/213460/unlock"><em>Unlock!</em> board game</a>,
which quite successfully recreates the experience of a scape room using just cards.
The only downside of the game is that after you&rsquo;ve solved each of the 3 rooms,
it looses the fun, as you already know the solution to the puzzles. So we though,
wouldn&rsquo;t it be cool to use this idea on a videogame, and have autogenerated puzzles
so that the fun never ends?</p>

<!-- more-->


<p>Lets not get overexcited though: we set as our first goal to design and implement a
static escape room puzzle, just to get familiar with the concept and the mechanics.
So that was the goal of today&rsquo;s hackday.</p>

<p>We started by brainstorming some ideas for items and fixtures in a possible
escape room. Then we started linking some of them together as dependencies,
following the <a href="http://grumpygamer.com/puzzle_dependency_charts">puzzle dependency graph technique</a>, that the good people at Lucasarts use to design their adventure games. It&rsquo;s surprisingly easy to start
doodling puzzles with this method!</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2017-05-29-escape-room/puzzle_whiteboard.png" alt="Puzzle whiteboarding" /></p>

<p>Then we got into implementing. We went for Unity3D, using fixed camera scenes for
the main room and each of the fixtures that we need to interact with. We
ended up having to dumb down a bit our original puzzle grahp design,
as otherwise we wouldn&rsquo;t have had time to implement it all in a day.</p>

<p>The end result is a short, but we hope that also clever escape room.
You can play right <a href="http://unity3d.coconauts.net/escaperoom/">here from your browser!</a></p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2017-05-29-escape-room/door.png" alt="door" /></p>

<p>We are quite happy with the result. It&rsquo;s the first time we make a puzzler game
and it turns out it is very rewarding: usually physics is the most frustrating
part of game development, and you have none of that in here. Your mind can focus
on designing and thinking puzzles rather than on tricky implementations. And
the game is fun without having to spend a lot of time polishing the mechanics.</p>

<p>As stated, our MVP is linear (except for a couple of passwords which are
generated randomly), but we plan to pick this project again to try to turn
it into something generative next time. Stay tuned!</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2017-05-29-escape-room/tv.png" alt="TV" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Water Ring Simulator]]></title>
    <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2017/03/27/water-rings-simulator/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-27T10:12:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2017/03/27/water-rings-simulator</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have more projects that posts in the blog, that&rsquo;s why a long ago we created a new new version of our first-game-ever: Water Rings.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="560" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5VBlgFSvP_w" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>




<!--more-->


<p>Water Rings Simulator is the new version of the classic toy game on Unity3d exlusive for Android.</p>

<p>This game features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Realisitc underwater physics</li>
<li>3D graphics</li>
<li>Mobile movement detection</li>
<li>Realistic visual effects</li>
<li>Transparent phone background (using camera to see behind it)</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s FREE!</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/posts/2017-04-20-water-rings-simulator/transparent.png" alt="game screenshot" /></p>

<p>Download the game for free on the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.coconauts.water3d">Android Play Store</a></p>

<p>Do you want us to keep expanding the game? let us know in the comments</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RPS: A Phaser.io Simple RTS]]></title>
    <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2017/02/18/rps-a-phaser-io-simple-rts/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-18T11:57:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2017/02/18/rps-a-phaser-io-simple-rts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you follow <a href="http://twitter.com/rephus">me</a> or <a href="http://twitter.com/coconauts">Coconauts</a> on Twitter, you might have seen some
GIFs about an RTS game we&rsquo;re developing on Phaser.io.</p>

<p>Codename: RPS (Rock, Paper, Scissors). Is a simple RTS (Real Strategy Game)
we&rsquo;re building using the Phaser.io framework for HTML5 games.</p>

<p>We aim to have a fun and complete game, with campaign, multiplayer
and with a fresh interface, compatible with mobile and touch devices.</p>

<p>The main selling point are its simple but effective mechanics.
Forget about hundreds of different units with their own powerups, multiple buildings,
or advanced research.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>This is some of the recent progress we&rsquo;ve made in the last 2-3 weeks.</p>

<ul>
<li>Minimap</li>
</ul>


<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Added a Minimap (bottom-rigth) to our game. It was easier than I expected <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/gamedev?src=hash">#gamedev</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/phaserIo?src=hash">#phaserIo</a> <a href="https://t.co/A0ATvb5ZxM">pic.twitter.com/A0ATvb5ZxM</a></p>&mdash; Coconauts (@coconauts) <a href="https://twitter.com/coconauts/status/826728173996015616">February 1, 2017</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<ul>
<li>Simple AI, sight area, and new map</li>
</ul>


<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Big progress on our RTS game in <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/phaserio?src=hash">#phaserio</a>: simple AI, sight area, new map and more! <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/gamedev?src=hash">#gamedev</a> <a href="https://t.co/jnxwofvm5c">pic.twitter.com/jnxwofvm5c</a></p>&mdash; Coconauts (@coconauts) <a href="https://twitter.com/coconauts/status/826161939478872069">January 30, 2017</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<ul>
<li>Emojis dialogs</li>
</ul>


<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Express yourself with in-game emojis <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/gamedev?src=hash">#gamedev</a> <a href="https://t.co/l6RoYpmrrm">pic.twitter.com/l6RoYpmrrm</a></p>&mdash; Javi Rengel (@rephus) <a href="https://twitter.com/rephus/status/825682597170786304">January 29, 2017</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>If you want to follow these updates closely, checkout our <a href="/projects/rps">Project page</a></p>

<p>And let us know if you want to give us feedback about how to improve the game !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2D Game Framework Comparison: Defold vs Phaser vs Game Maker]]></title>
    <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2017/01/09/2d-game-framework-comparison/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-09T10:42:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2017/01/09/2d-game-framework-comparison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We wanted to start a building new 2D game ideas we have in mind, and we thought
our favorite 3D platform so far (Unity3D) was not optimal enough to build a fully 2D game.
And despite having experience with some other frameworks like LibGDX (as we built
<a href="/projects/timebomb2">Exploding Bunnies</a> ) along with some other Ludum Dare games,
we wanted to see if there is something better.</p>

<p>After some investigation, we narrowed the list to Defold vs Phaser.io vs Game Maker,
 so we decided to give them a try by building a quick Pong demo in those 3 frameworks,
and gather some conclusions before we start building our next 2D game.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Defold</h2>

<p>Propietary framework made by King (experts on mobile games). They have built a
promising editor with a lot of great features, like version control and easy deployment to multiple platforms.
Although it&rsquo;s still on Beta, it sounds like this might be a trully solid option.</p>

<p>It took me some time to get used to the new concepts like the atlas and the collection, plus all the properties.
After a while, the whole framework reminded me of Unity3D, but simpler.
On the other hand, the current editor, which is based on Eclipse, gave me bad memories;
fortunately they&rsquo;re moving  to a <a href="http://www.defold.com/roadmap/">cloure based editor</a> now.
I got blocked during almost an hour because of this
<a href="https://forum.defold.com/t/scaling-collision-object-when-game-object-is-scaled-def-521/547">scaled collision object bug</a>
until I discovered the useful debug option on game settings.</p>

<iframe src='http://html5.coconauts.net/2d-framework-comparison/defold/' width=650 height=350></iframe>


<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.defold.com/showcase/">Showcase</a></p></li>
<li><p>Language: Lua</p></li>
<li><p>Getting started: <a href="http://www.defold.com/tutorials/getting-started/">http://www.defold.com/tutorials/getting-started/</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p><img src='http://coconauts.net/images/posts/2017-01-09-2d-framework/defold-editor.png'/></p>

<h4>Pros:</h4>

<ul>
<li>Free</li>
<li>Visual editor</li>
<li>Available on Linux</li>
<li>Multiplatform</li>
<li>Performance</li>
<li>Version control friendly (+integrated)</li>
<li>Integrated game analytics</li>
</ul>


<h4>Cons:</h4>

<ul>
<li>Propietary solution</li>
<li>Still beta</li>
<li><p>Found bugs while building demo</p></li>
<li><p>Score:  7 / 10</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Get our demo <a href="https://github.com/rephus/pong-sample-defold">here</a></p>

<h2>Phaser.io</h2>

<p>Pretty popular simple opensource framework  with a great community and tons of examples.</p>

<p>While building this demo, I found it was surprisingly easy to start with,
plus the documentation and the API was very clear and advanced.</p>

<p>Things like <code>game.world.centerX</code> instead of doing <code>game.world.width / 2</code> or
<code>body.collideWorldBounds = True</code> really impressed me.</p>

<iframe src='http://html5.coconauts.net/2d-framework-comparison/phaser/' width=650 height=350></iframe>


<ul>
<li><p>Language: Javascript</p></li>
<li><p>Getting started: <a href="http://phaser.io/tutorials/getting-started">http://phaser.io/tutorials/getting-started</a></p></li>
<li><p>Pong tutorial: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3egKs7b86j0">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3egKs7b86j0</a></p></li>
</ul>


<h4>Pros:</h4>

<ul>
<li>Open source (but with a company behind it)</li>
<li>Available on Linux</li>
<li>HTML5 (multiplatform)</li>
<li>Great community</li>
<li>Version control capabilities</li>
</ul>


<h4>Cons:</h4>

<ul>
<li>No official Visual editor</li>
<li><p>No direct Android exporting (cordova/cocoon required)</p></li>
<li><p>Score: 8 / 10</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Get our demo <a href="https://github.com/rephus/pong-sample-phaser">here</a></p>

<h2>Game Maker</h2>

<p>Probably one of the oldests game frameworks and still pretty popular,
I remember using this like 10 years ago, before I knew anything about programming.
And to be honest, it hasn&rsquo;t changed that much since then.</p>

<p>The fact the free version only allows to generate window executables and
that the studio only runs on Windows was conclusive enough,
but also the whole framework is no much different from the others,
if you know programming.</p>

<p>Some of the best indie games have been made with this framework like:</p>

<ul>
<li>Spelunky</li>
<li>Hyper Light Drifter</li>
<li>Nuclear Throne</li>
<li><p>Hotline Miami</p></li>
<li><p>Language: Game Maker Language</p></li>
<li><p>Getting started: <a href="http://www.yoyogames.com/learn">http://www.yoyogames.com/learn</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p><img src='http://coconauts.net/images/posts/2017-01-09-2d-framework/gamemaker-editor.png'/></p>

<h4>Pros:</h4>

<ul>
<li>Visual editor</li>
<li>No programming skills required</li>
<li>Seems to be the indie industry standard</li>
</ul>


<h4>Cons:</h4>

<ul>
<li>Propietary solution</li>
<li>Windows only editor</li>
<li>No multiplatform (free version)</li>
<li>Uses its own scripting language</li>
<li>Version control issues</li>
<li><p>Slow runnable</p></li>
<li><p>Score:  3 / 10</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclussions</h2>

<p>We decided Phaser.io to be our next 2D framework. Of the 3 it was the faster and easiest to get started with. Defold sounds like with some polish it might be a sounder solution to use for real projects (for example, the mobile export is managed a lot better, or the integrated analytics are a bit plus); but the bugs we found on Defold while building this simple demo scared us a bit. Once it matures we might give it another go, but for now Phaser fits the bill for our purposes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Improve Classic Nintendo Games]]></title>
    <link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/12/29/how-improve-nintendo/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-29T10:42:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2016/12/29/how-improve-nintendo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Although the Nintendo Mini has been a great success, and the best way of recreating our childhood
experience with a great collection of classic Nintendo games; There are a lot of things still Nintendo
can do to our beloved classic games in order to let us play those classic games in a complete new (and refreshing) way. They don&rsquo;t even need to do it on a new old mini console, but on their virtual store on WiiU or NX (switch)</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/2016-12-29-how-improve-nintendo/nes-mini.jpg" alt="achievement"></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Some of these ideas have already been proved possible in our <a href="http://retrophies.win">Retrophies</a> project, just by taking the original game, with no ROM hacking involved but just checking the memory values in the emulator, so imagine what Nintendo can do with their original games,
something they already tried on the great Nes Remix compilation.</p>

<h2>Achievements</h2>

<p>Some people love them, some people hate them, but it&rsquo;s true they are a good way of motivating people
on playing games again with an objective in mind. Won&rsquo;t you play Super Mario Bros again if I tell you
you will get an official reward by finishing it ? Maybe the brand new Nintendo coins.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/2016-12-29-how-improve-nintendo/achievement.png" alt="achievement"></p>

<p>This was the main feature of Retrophies and it was pretty fun to build and play.</p>

<h2>Multiplayer</h2>

<p>Another concept we tested on Retrophies, having the capability of see (or interact) with
other players in real time while you play.</p>

<p><img src="http://coconauts.net/images/posts/2016-12-29-how-improve-nintendo/multiplayer.png" alt="multiplayer"></p>

<p>Sounds like playing New Super Mario Bros on Super Mario Bros.</p>

<h2>Scoreboards</h2>

<p>Who is the fastest player to finish World 1-1 on Super Mario Bros ? This is a concept we
are still working on Retrophies.</p>

<p>Nintendo can add official scoreboard to most of their games. I mean, speedrunners
do this with most Nintendo games already, think about all the crazy Ocarina of Time speedrunnes available, why don&rsquo;t make it official.</p>

<h2>Maker version of classic games</h2>

<p>Remember Mario maker and how fun was to build scenarios on Super Mario ? Then why not integrating
this function on existing games ? This is also a possibility that we could integrate in
Retrophies in the future (by adding blocks or items in the screen in memory).</p>

<p>Do you have another idea for twisted classic Nintendo games ?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
