<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title><![CDATA[Tag: featured | Coconauts]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/tags/featured/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/"/>
<updated>2016-06-27T23:05:32+01:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/</id>
<author>
<name><![CDATA[Coconauts]]></name>
<email><![CDATA[admin@coconauts.net]]></email>
</author>
<generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

<entry>
<title type="html"><![CDATA[Add list of featured posts to Octopress]]></title>
<link href="http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/09/08/add-featured-posts-to-octopress/"/>
<updated>2015-09-08T20:03:19+01:00</updated>
<id>http://coconauts.net/blog/2015/09/08/add-featured-posts-to-octopress</id>
<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago we were requested to add a list of featured posts to an index page in Octopress.
So we did a bit of research about how Octopress + Jekyll + Lyquid template internally works.
And we ended up with a nice solution that you can easily replicate in your own blog.</p>

<p>In this post we will show you how to add your own custom list of featured octopress posts like in <a href="http://coconauts.net#featured-posts">Coconauts</a></p>

<!--more-->


<p>The first thing you need to do is to add a new custom tag to your posts, we will call it <code>featured</code></p>

<h2>```</h2>

<p>layout: post
author: Javier Rengel
published: true</p>

<h2>featured: true</h2>

<p>```</p>

<p>Create a new template file called <code>featured_posts.html</code> inside your <code>source/_includes</code> folder,
with this content:</p>

<p>
```</p>

<div class="row">
   {% assign featured_count = '' %}
   {% for post in site.posts %}
       {% if post.featured and featured_count.size < 3 %}
          {% capture featured_count %}{{ featured_count }}*{% endcapture %}
           <div class="col-sm-4 col-lg-4 column featured-post">
              <a class='post-link' href="{{ root_url }}{{ post.url }}">{{ post.title | titlecase }}</a>
              <p>{{ post.content | strip_html | condense_spaces | truncate:300 }}</p>
           </div>
       {% endif %}
   {% endfor %}
</div>


<p>```
</p>

<p>Then you can list your three most recent featured posts in every page you want just by adding this code to your markdown or HTML file:</p>

<p>
<code>
{% include featured_posts.html %}
</code>
</p>

<p>Just remember to adapt your HTML code and your CSS to your needs (this one is based on <a href="http://getbootstrap.com/">bootstrap</a>).</p>

<h3>Featured posts</h3>

<p><div class="row">
   
   
       
          
           <div class="col-sm-4 col-lg-4 column">
              <a class='post-link' href="/blog/2016/06/13/lightning-dodge-o-matic/">Lightning-dodge-O-matic</a>
              <p>If you have played Final Fantasy X, either its original version for PS2 or its remastered version
for PS4 and PSVita, you might remember Thunder Plains and its lightning dodge challenge
to get the Mars sigil. It&rsquo;s quite challenging and it might take a while. I once got it (and I have a PS2 &hellip;</p>
           </div>
       
   
       
          
           <div class="col-sm-4 col-lg-4 column">
              <a class='post-link' href="/blog/2016/05/19/build-house-in-3d-with-blender-unity3d/">We Built Our House With Unity3D and Blender</a>
              <p>We moved home a few months ago to a beautiful house in the country side in UK,
outside the expensive area of London, but close enough to commute daily. As soon as we moved in, we built a simple version of our home in 3D on Blender to help us decorate. And then we integrated the 3D model into &hellip;</p>
           </div>
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
          
           <div class="col-sm-4 col-lg-4 column">
              <a class='post-link' href="/blog/2016/02/04/coconauts-ci-nodejs/">Coconauts CI, a Lightweight CI Built on NodeJS</a>
              <p>CIs are good, as soon as your projects grow, having a continuous integration software
that manages all your apps and deployments is really useful. We have been using a self-hosted
jenkins instance in our server for a few years already, and we have some
interesting things with it. However, we have &hellip;</p>
           </div>
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
       
   
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
</entry>

</feed>